<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>26. of August, 1647. To all the vvorld to view, and to all men of common sencc [sic] Christianity or humanity, to judge of Thomas Coningsby of Northmynis in the county of Hartford Esquire, now prisoner in the Tower of London. And of continuance under slavish and most inhumaine gaole tyrannie over his person, the space of foure yeares, eight months, and most illegall proceeding and oppressive, violence and villanies, (by indirect carriage) to his totall ruine, presents both the one and other to judge of and shewes.</title>
            <author>Coningsby, Thomas, 1591-1654.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80353</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C5879</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E406_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201910</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862393</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862393</idno>
            <idno type="VID">160485</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80353)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 160485)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 64:E406[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>26. of August, 1647. To all the vvorld to view, and to all men of common sencc [sic] Christianity or humanity, to judge of Thomas Coningsby of Northmynis in the county of Hartford Esquire, now prisoner in the Tower of London. And of continuance under slavish and most inhumaine gaole tyrannie over his person, the space of foure yeares, eight months, and most illegall proceeding and oppressive, violence and villanies, (by indirect carriage) to his totall ruine, presents both the one and other to judge of and shewes.</title>
                  <author>Coningsby, Thomas, 1591-1654.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed in the yeare. 1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Thomas Coningsby by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "7ber [i.e. September] 7th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Coningsby, Thomas, 1591-1654 --  Imprisonment --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Detention of persons --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:160485:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>26. of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1647.</p>
            <p>TO ALL THE WORLD TO view, and to all men of common ſence Chriſtianity or humanity, to judge of <hi>Thomas Coningsby</hi> of <hi>Northmynis</hi> in the County of HARTFORD <hi>Eſquire,</hi> now Priſoner in the <hi>TOWER OF LONDON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And of continuance under ſlaviſh and moſt inhumaine Gaole tyrannie over his perſon, the ſpace of foure yeares, eight months, and moſt illegall proceeding and oppreſſive, violence and Villanies, (by indirect carriage) to his totall ruine, preſents both the one and other to judge of and ſhewes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Yeare. 1647</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:160485:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:160485:2"/>
            <head>26. of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1647. TO ALL THE VVORLD TO view, and to all men of common ſence, Chriſtianity or humanity to iudge of.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat in <hi>November</hi> 1642. He being a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man borne in that County, and inhabitant there all his life time; was by the Kings Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty made Shriffe of the ſaid County, and a Commiſſion under his ſaid Majeſtyes great Seale (the authority of which was then un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable) for executing the ſaid Office, and a writ directed to adminiſter ſuch oathes as lawfully were uſual to the truſt committed to the Shreiſes, all which were accoor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly by me taken, and in <hi>January</hi> following it pleaſed his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty to direct his writ of <hi>non omittas</hi> with a certain number of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations, commanding me by the ſaid authority under his great Seale to publiſh the ſame in the County, which unavoydable by Office, and Oath <hi>I</hi> was bound to performe, and performing the ſame at the Town of St. <hi>Albons</hi> the 13. of the ſaid <hi>Ianuary</hi> in a peaceable manner, not doing any the leaſt thing in my own inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt or accompanied with any force in doing the ſame. I was that day forceably ſeized upon (without any warrant or authority) by one <hi>Pat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſon</hi> with a Troop of 80. horſe, and ſo violently carryed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and brought to <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> the 15. of <hi>Janu.</hi> where indeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be brought and heard in the houſe of Commons, which could not be obtained, but that night unexamined ſent priſoner
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:160485:3"/>to London houſe, but by what warrant, or for what cauſe I know not to this day, continuing in this condition till the 13 of <hi>March</hi> 1642. I was by a ſtrict warrant ſigned, <hi>Miles Corbet</hi> ſeiſed on by one that called himſelfe a Sargeants deputy, and carryed before THE ſaid <hi>Corbet</hi> in the Court of Wards Chamber, not exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined at all concerning the cauſe of my then impriſonment, and <hi>Corbet</hi> leaving me under Guarde going into the houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, what report <hi>Corbet</hi> falſely and ungroundedly made of me to the houſe, nor upon what cauſe or reaſon, more then a mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned order in this warrant of my Commitment whereon groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, I could never ſince learne, the warrant here incerted.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="warrant">
                        <p>By vertue of an Order this day made by the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons now aſſembled in Parliament, Theſe are to will and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire you or your deputy, forthwith to receive from the Sarjeant at Armes or his deputy, the body of Mr. <hi>Coningsby</hi> high Sheriff of the County of <hi>Hertford</hi> into his Majeſties Priſon of the Tower. And him there to keepe as cloſe priſoner, during the pleaſure of the ſaid Commons; and this ſhall be your ſufficient warant,</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <date>this 13 of <hi>March</hi> 1642,</date>
                           </dateline>
                           <signed>William Lenthall Speaker.</signed>
                        </closer>
                        <argument>
                           <p>To the Leivetenant of the Tower or his Deputy.</p>
                        </argument>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Vnder this commitment. from the ſaid 13 of <hi>March</hi> 1642. till ninth of <hi>May</hi> 1644. I did continue in the Tower without any charge brought againſt mee, and with what tyranicall uſage till then, and moſt part ſince would draw it juſtly to a queſtion whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the place ſtood in any part of Chriſtendome, or the Goalers bred under any rules of humanity, and THE ſaid <hi>Corbet</hi> as a Committee for the Tower pretended to be their authority, for all their extortions and outrages, now that on the 9. of <hi>May,</hi> I here divide my time of impriſonment it fal on thus that my wife paying in the country all 5. and twenteth parts, and pay in all rates, untill the Sequeſtration of my reall eſtate and totally rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me of my perſonall eſtate (as here followes) I continued un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtioned, till one Sir <hi>William Brereton</hi> by ordinance of the Lords and Commons publiſhed in print, dated <hi>Die Martis</hi> 26. <hi>Martii</hi> 1644. <hi>inter ali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> in that ordinance has theſe enſuing words. And be it farther ordained by the Lords and Commons,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:160485:3"/>that the perſonall eſtates of all ſuch Delinquents and Papiſts within the <hi>Cittie</hi> of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and within 20 miles of the ſame, not Sequeſtered nor diſcovered, and which ſhall be diſcovered by the ſaid Sir <hi>William Brereton,</hi> or ſuch perſon or perſons, as he ſhall authoriſe, under his hand and ſeale for that purpoſe, within two months next after the publiſhing in print of the ordinance: ſhall be allowed unto the ſaid Sir <hi>William Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reton,</hi> for the farther advancement of the ſaid ſervice, provided that the ſaid concealed eſtates exceede not the ſumme of 5000 l. And that the ſaid Sir <hi>William Brereton</hi> or any perſon authorized by him as aforeſaid nor any of them, ſhall poſſeſſe themſelves of the ſaid Papiſts or Delinquents eſtates, before he or they acquaint the Committee of Lords and Commons for Sequeſtrations there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, to the end they may judge of the Delinquencie of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, before his or their eſtates be taken away.</p>
            <p>Here is the limitations of <hi>Breretons</hi> Ordinance, yet ſhortly after it appeared by his proceedings, he procured an order from the Houſe of Commons, only to the Committee of Examinations, to examine and judge of the Delinquencie; marke here (right or wrong.) <hi>Brereton</hi> playes a ſure game with me in <hi>Corbets</hi> Chair-ſhip.</p>
            <p>1. <hi>May,</hi> A Warrant of that Committee iſſues out for ſeizing Ms. <hi>Conningsbys</hi> Eſtate, and Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> his eſtate for ſending Horſe and Armes to <hi>Oxford,</hi> and for entertaining and ſending Intelligence thether.</p>
            <p>3. <hi>May,</hi> (No Delinquencie examined) the Warrant was exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, both their goods within doore and without, Inventored, ſeverall bonds with Sureties, required for ſecuring them, or elſe to have Soldiers put upon them, to looke to their goods, and to avoid that, bonds were accordingly given.</p>
            <p>6. <hi>May.</hi> Both were ſerved with order of that Committee of Examination to appeare, the 7. of <hi>May,</hi> which they accordingly did, being called and having nothing againſt Ms. <hi>Conningsby,</hi> the Soliciter was blamed for troubling her, and ſhe diſcharged. But here begins a charge againſt me by one <hi>Prices</hi> information, to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:160485:4"/>the Soliciter, that Mr. <hi>Conningsby</hi> had ſet the Commiſſion of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ray on foot in that Country; hereupon it is appointed that I be brought before <hi>Corbet,</hi> on <hi>Thurſday</hi> following, my wife acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them with the ſciſure of her goods, her barnes, locked, her houſe full of Soldiers moved, ſhe might have neceſſarie reliefe for her and her childrens livelyhood out of her goods, and not be accountable for what the Soldiers took, who were unruly, and had continued there all the winter till then, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee declared accordingly, Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> is likewiſe diſcharged of the ſame lying charge.</p>
            <p>9 <hi>May</hi> I am brought before this Committee, no Commſſion of Array but charged for the Proclamations at Saint <hi>Albons</hi> the date aforeſaid in <hi>Ianuary</hi> before the Ordinance of Sequeſtration, for that Ordinance was not in being till <hi>March</hi> following, and upon one <hi>Browne</hi> (they ſaid Lawyer) his learned expoud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the words has or ſhall in the ordinance adjudged by that Committee a Delinquent though done before the ſaid Ordinance and in the lawfull diſcharge of my ſaid office, of Sheriff wicke, the tye of oath than lay upon me and juſtly puniſhable by Law, if not executed being the Kings Writs. This judgement of the Committee thus pact by <hi>Brereton,</hi> and as I may iuſtly ſuſpect by the practiſe of <hi>Litton</hi> as by the ſequell, (who in the beginning of this Parliament before a Committee in the court of requeſts, and the contrary teſtified by two of his own ranke there, and notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly known to hundreds of people preſent at the occaſion, did lyingly declare and teſtifie before that Committee (that at the Election of Burgeſſes for the Burrow of St. <hi>Albons</hi> (and my ſelfe ſtanding for an Election to ſerve this Parliament) he ſeeme brought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhoolders from my lodging to the place where the Kings writ wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to be read and before reading the ſame. and in his view, as farre as the turning into the open market place from the end of a cloſe ſtreet, which is fully the length of <hi>Weſt-minſter hall,</hi> yet now upon this occaſion, my ſonne ioyning with my wife, applyed themſelves to crave his aſſiſtance in a Petition of Appeale to the Commons houſe againſt the irregular in the proceedings, and moſt uniuſt upon the matter of proceeding of this Committee, and ſhewed him their Petition, the Lawyer
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:160485:4"/>
               <hi>Browne</hi> was likewiſe acquainted with it, <hi>Littons</hi> diſcouragement to them, and advice was to compound with <hi>Brereton</hi> for he ſaid the Houſe would not alter the Votes and judgement of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee, and Lawyer <hi>Brown,</hi> his anſwer was, that if they went that way, my ſonne would utterly undoe his father, and upon this they deſiſted and were diſcouraged to proceed, and ſome few dayes after, <hi>Litton</hi> pretending friendſhip, and they applying them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to <hi>Litton,</hi> and in <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> attending him, and in diſcours of my ſaid ruin and ſad conditon upon this Iudgement meeting <hi>Browne,</hi> aſked him why he gave at the Committee that opinion upon has or ſhall againſt Mr. <hi>Coningsby</hi> anſwered why were you ſo earneſt to have me there, I underſtood it to be in frendſhip to Sir <hi>William Brereton,</hi> or words to this effect.</p>
            <p>My wife hereupon, prepared another Petition to the houſe of Commons wherein her ſon joynes ſhowes it to <hi>Brereton</hi> who gives her ſmoth language, and ſeemes willing to referre the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to Sir William <hi>Litton,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt</hi> to ſtand to what they ſhould think good therein, and in the Intrim <hi>Brereton</hi> cauſed the goods to be valued by creatures of his owne, contraty to what the ordinance declares, my wife offers <hi>Brereton</hi> a compoſition which he excepts not of, goe ſuddenly for <hi>Cheſheire</hi> ſhee is threatened of his Agent, all her goods to be taken away, upon which ſhee Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions the Committee of examination who referred the petition to the Committee of the Countie they appoynt a day to heare the ſame.</p>
            <p>1 <hi>Iuly Breretons</hi> Agent brings to my houſe one <hi>Hanle</hi> and <hi>Geering</hi> two of the under Sequeſtrators, and revewe, and value the goods, but permit not my wife to be privie to the values now made, nor formerly not to have any coppie thereof, the Agent pretending haſt, and miſſing ſome things of common uſe to the houſe, in the places firſt inventored entred the ſame as wanting, though my wife then told him they were neceſſarily uſed in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther roomes, and ſhould againſt the day of ſale be ſet in their firſt places which was accordingly done.</p>
            <p>2 <hi>Iuly</hi> upon debate of my wives Petition referred as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, <hi>Breretons</hi> Agent preſent the Committee, ordred the bringing
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:160485:5"/>in the inventory next morning, and my wife to have the 5. part of the perſonall eſtate ſet her out.</p>
            <p>3 <hi>Iuly</hi> the inventory is brought in, amounting to 549. pound wherein the timber felled and the rents were not included but left to farther order, the Committee with conſent of <hi>Breretons</hi> Agent did farther order that 9 pounds of 149 I ſhould be ſtroken out for the goods they marked with a croſſe, as belonging to the Houſe. and that 108. be allotted to her for the fifth part of 540. l.</p>
            <p>And for equall ſetting forth five part, Mr. <hi>Grob</hi> and Mr. <hi>Brooks</hi> withother neighbours, or any two of them, were ordered to joyne with <hi>Breretons</hi> Agent for doing thereof out of the Parcells in-ventored.</p>
            <p>But the ſame day the Agent proceeding to ſell the goods, the perſons ordered for ſetting out the 5th. part at my wives requeſt, tendred to the Agent for her 5th. part, the Cowes, the corne in the Barne, the Hogs, as they were ſerverally appriſed, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ue of her 5th. part to be ſet out in ſheep, or houſhould ſtuffe, but the Agent refuſed the ſame, and <hi>Oduiſell</hi> the Soliciter of the County being then brought thither by the Agent, made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe another diviſion giving her thereby the 5th. part of the Cowes, which were in the whole number 21. Cowes, the 5th. part of the ſheep, Hogs, Corne upon the ground, and all the goods in her owne lodging Chamber, the little Parlor, and the Kitchin which my wife, and perſons ordered to make the diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on oppoſed, chiefly becauſe thoſe goods were over valued in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of all the other, out of preſumption ſhe would take them, being ſo neceſſary for her owne uſe, and ſome of them her ſonnes being ſo marked in the inventory, as likewiſe that two of the Cowes were by the Soldiers that quartered there, killed and ſpent 10. or 12. dayes after the ſeiſure, and by <hi>Breretons,</hi> Soldiers that quartered 8. or 9. dayes after the other were gone, and by ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of his owne Agents, and for that halfe of the ſheep and thoſe of the beſt were driven away long before by <hi>Breretons</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents, without ſaile or authority, the Ladyes good haſwifery at <hi>Chaiſoe Bury,</hi> not to be otherwiſe provided, and the good wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man much offended, that the Cowes ſtaid ſo long, whether the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:160485:5"/>moſt part of them were to be caried, which conſiderations made my wife, and the ſaid perſons deſired a more equal diviſion which was denied, then my wife deſired (they proceeding to ſale) that the houſhold ſtuffe allotted her might likewiſe be put to ſale, and ſhee have the taking or refuſing them, or the firſt of the monies upon the ſale of all the houſhold ſtuffe, for ſomuch of her 5, part which likewiſe was denied her, then did ſhee, and the ſaid par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons appoynted deſired they might chuſe one of their 4. Cowes for my wife, according to <hi>Oduiſells</hi> diviſion, which was likewiſe refuſed, and 9. of the beſt of them firſt choſen out by <hi>Breretons</hi> Agent, and driven away without putting them to ſale, 4. of thoſe 9. being more ualuable by much then 6. of thoſe left behind, of all which a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificate was then made by thoſe perſons appoynted for the diviſion and returned to the Committee.</p>
            <p>And having ſo informed the Committee of the miſcari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, and <hi>Oduiſells</hi> jugling, finding <hi>Oduiſells</hi> power with the Committee to great for her, ſhee ſubmitted to his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion, ſo as ſhee might have benefit of that for the future, the pretence being that <hi>Oduiſells</hi> deviſion was for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage (as they call it) of the State, and thoſe things would yeild moſt, and readieſt mony to the State, that were denied to her by the firſt deviſion tendred, and how farre it tended to the benefit of the State, I deſire all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt men to judge of, except you will have it that knaves be countenanced in their villanies, the Committee Silli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citer <hi>Brereton,</hi> and his Agent being all like to like.</p>
            <p>The 9. Cowes of the beſt driven away as aforeſaid, without being put to ſale at all, out of the reſedue of them my wife had only 2. for her fift part, and thoſe killed by the Soldiers ſet on her acount by abatement, and the reſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:160485:6"/>
               <hi>Hale</hi> the under Sequeſtrator took without being put to ſale at 2. pound 10. ſhillings a Cowe, as inventered, which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers underſtanding, deſired the Solicitor that they might be put to ſale as other goods and the houſehold-ſtuffe were by the candle, and thereupon they were put to ſale, and 3. pound 9. ſhilings a peece bid for them, and ſo cari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed away, yet did <hi>Hale</hi> ſo carrie the buſineſſe and claimed them as his right by the former privat ſale of them, that he got the Agent to referre it to <hi>Oduiſell,</hi> who adjudged the firſt ſale to <hi>Hale</hi> good at 2. pound 10. ſhillings a Cowe, and depaſtured then <hi>Gratis,</hi> in my ground all the yeare after for the Benefit of the State, and if <hi>Brereton</hi> examin his account I beleeve the monie is not paid yet.</p>
            <p>The corne in the Barne was another particular my wiſe deſired, at the rate inventoried which was 45. pound, and this ſold at 41. pound payable by 5. pound a Weeke, which was 4. pound loſſe to the State as they call it, and not ſold for ready mony, ſo that though the publique was pretended all was done to their own private ends, ſo they robbed me of all, there State pretended was much coſened by knaves, and my wife of the benefit of the Ordinance of her 5. part very much, for the houſhold-ſtuffe put to ſale, they had ready monie for nothing elſe.</p>
            <p>In this ſtraite my wife was in and nothing left to keepe her, her children and familie, from ſtarving, (but the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull goodneſſe of hers and mine eldeſt ſonne Harry <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningsby,</hi> upon whom an eſtate was ſetled on his Marriage) and ſhee not being ſuffered to have any thing out of her own goods propper for livelyhod, under hand imployes one Cow <hi>William</hi> who had for divers yeares beene Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee over her hogs, to bid for and buy for her the wheat in the barne, which was to be paid for as aforeſaid, which
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:160485:6"/>accordingly did at 43. pound, went the next market day to make ſale of what was threſhed, and according to his diſpoſition became very drunke, this diſcourages my wife in her bargan and her new baylie, and allowes him not to market any more, her old Committeeman sa aforeſaid growes diſcontent, aplyes himſelfe to the Committee at Saint <hi>Albons,</hi> claimes from them, to have the bargan to himſelfe, my wife rightly poſſeſſes that Committee how the buſineſſe ſtood, of his barganing in her behalfe, yet this righteous Committee in their great wiſdomes and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, order Cow <hi>William</hi> to have the bargan to himſelfe, to breake open the Barne dores againſt her, and put him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in poſſeſſion, but now ſee Gods great providence to her in ſo deepe diſtreſſe, ſo to mollifie the heart of this one raſcall towards her, Cow <hi>William</hi> is content to take her to halves in the bargen, to pay for all the worke and carriage, pay <hi>Brereton,</hi> and ſo to devide with her, the one halfe, and upon his account brought her in above 20. quarters of wheat, now judge all men by this account how my goods were ſold for the beneifit of the State, and how ſeaſonable a reliefe in ſo great a diſtreſſe as this was, when being rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of all wee had by the greater theeves, thus to be reliev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by ſuch a raſcall.</p>
            <p>The ſame day the ſale was, they diſcovered in a garret roome under a trape dore ſome goods, 5. feather beds ſome trunkes of linen, and pewter, two riding ſutes of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens furniture for horſes, of velver, 12. halberds, 8. muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets with other goods, ſome of theſe goods being my ſonns and his wives, and put there long before ſequeſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for ſecuring them from ſoldiers and plundring, and ſome of them my daughter in lawes put there in the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter before for ſafety upon their going from thence to live at <hi>London,</hi> and upon diſcovering of theſe goods my ſonns
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:160485:7"/>man being there, acquainted <hi>Oduiſells</hi> therewith, that ſuch goods were his Maſters and Miſtriſes, and laid there by him, offered oath for the ſame and deſired time till next morning, and hee would fetch the inventory of ſuch goods as were his maſters, and bring the next day far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proofe, this was denied him, the beds, and pewter, halbeards, and muskets, put to ſale; lynnen and the furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture had away without inventoring any, they ſold the 5. beds, for 9. pound, and my wife borrowed monie and paid it there preſently for one of them five pounds, for herſelfe to ly upon, ſo good was ſuch furniture as they put upon her in her own chamber, and of all theſe goods ſhee has had no account of a 5. part, nor my ſonne of what of thoſe goods was taken away of his.</p>
            <p>And my wife not ſuffered to have the deviſion ſhee deſired, ſo ſhee had not the benefit of <hi>Ondui ſells</hi> diviſion for all the Cowes, but two were had a way, as before is ſhowed, and thoſe two ſhee was forced to keepe out of their way, and the ſheep likewiſe that were left were had away, and ſold to <hi>Halle,</hi> and ſhee left for account to her 5. part of thoſe that were killed and eaten by the Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, and for the Corne in the ground which was ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther particular, out of which ſhee was to have a 5. part by <hi>Oduiſells</hi> diviſion, one <hi>Andrewes</hi> the firſt ſetter on of <hi>Brereton</hi> upon this buſineſſe, the new admitted Vicker of the pariſh, as buſie for his own profit as any other, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rector in chiefe of the whole matter, and in truth as unconſcionable a knave as <hi>Brereton</hi> himſelfe, or any of his inſtruments, though he were furniſhed with ſome out of Turneball <hi>Street,</hi> and <hi>Charter-houſelaine,</hi> and ſome of the pertious dames of theſe places to boote, whether many Cart loads of my goods were brought, this <hi>Andrewes</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:160485:7"/>without my wives privity, and not according to the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance by the candle, did ſell away all the crone, and ſhee deſiring to have ſome ſhare, as moſt convenient for lively-hood, and having neither mony nor meanes to ſend to market was denied it, and yet it was not ſold for ready mony, but payable at <hi>Chriſtmaſſe,</hi> and upon her complaint hereupon to the Committee, and debate thereupon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending the publique good, and examining of what my wife had received of her 5. part, which was about 50. pound, and of that 50. pound 44. pound was in houſhold ſtuffe not worth halfe the mony, after the rate of their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſing of thoſe goods they caried away.</p>
            <p>30 <hi>July</hi> the ſaid <hi>Andrews,</hi> preſent it was ordred that my wife be paid 58. pound in mony for the reſedue of her 5. part, if cauſe were not ſhewed to the contrary that day fortnight.</p>
            <p>The ſame day ordred my wife ſhall receive her 5. part of the Ladie <hi>dayes</hi> rents, and of the money the Timber was ſould for, the ſale of which Timber was there tendred (in writing of his own hand) by <hi>Andrewes</hi> wherein he afirms in writing the quantity of the Timber that the ſame was meaſured and ſold (among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers therein named) by one George <hi>Oliver</hi> a carpenter, ſent by my wife for that purpoſe who thought the rate ſufficient, by w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> falſe and deceitfull coſonage and forgery of that lying <hi>Andrewes</hi> (for he was excellent at that &amp; after well known to the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mittee themſelves for his qualities) without oppoſition the committee allowed the ſale, but afterward upon examination of the matter, it was found otherwiſe, for <hi>Oliver</hi> never meaſured nor ſold any of it, nor knew of the ſale, nor was he ſent unto by my wife for that purpoſe, nor was the ſale made by the candle or otherwiſe, but in privat, nor the Timber ever meaſured by any but the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penter that brought it, and the quantety entred as he ſaid it was ſold for, at 18. ſhilings <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r</hi> load, which others hard by ſold at 1. pound 5. ſhilings the loade, and the ends ſuffered by <hi>Andrews</hi> to goe with the timber ſave aniy account, of great which were value and not mentioned
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:160485:8"/>in his note, &amp; as large as the carpenter pleaſed to make them, which cheat was for the benefit of the State and my wife.</p>
            <p>Now for a cloſe after my ſo long durance without any cauſe or other matter then as aforeſaid, and the indirect proceeding of <hi>Breretons,</hi> before the Committee of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination neither warranted by the generall ordinance of Sequeſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or his particular Ord that direcs the iudgement of cauſe Sequeſtration to Lords and Commons, and not to any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Iudicators; a ſupſequent order of Commons only to that Committee ſhewes where this <hi>Breretons</hi> ſtrength lay to ruine me, and carried on before a Committee where the dores were kept ſhut, the buſineſſe carried among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, where is to be preſumed he had a ſtrong party of the Committee made ſure, and councell prepared, whereas on the contrary, (after falſe pretence to bring his ends a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout) I am ſent for, to be brought out of a Gaole, not knowing upon what ground, or what was to be objected againſt me, without counſell or knowledge who were to be my Iudges, but am confident if the Ordinances had beene accordingly proceeded in before the right and open Committee, where clooſe dealing carieth not cauſes, and others are free to here, though they only to Iudge, <hi>Brere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons</hi> greedy ends upon me, nor the malice of others, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon the cauſe it ſelfe, nor <hi>Brownes</hi> has, or ſhall, would have ſo carried on my ruine, this clooſe dealing is ever the contrary to juſt dealing, and I once heard a No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Lord coming out of the Starre-Chamber, upon a hard ſenſure of a privat Gentleman, wee that are a few give judgement heere, but they are many more that judge us.</p>
            <p>The order of the Committee on the 30. of <hi>July,</hi> that allowes her 58. pound to make up her 5. part, is oppoſed by <hi>Andrews</hi> who had got the monie into his own hands, who pretends Malignanſie, &amp; imbeſiling againſt my wife,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:160485:8"/>ſpares no meanes to ſuborne proofes, makes his ſtrength to countenance his malice, and cheating one <hi>Bradſhaw,</hi> and <hi>Steele,</hi> Lawyers as I heare, by whom ſhe is for a full yeare toſſed from Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mittee above &amp; Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mittee, below &amp; after ſeveral refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences of their procuring here, &amp; certificats from the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Committee, and nothing to be proved, &amp; <hi>Andrewes</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice perjury and villanies, ſo diſcovered by them that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, and as I take it certified to the Committee here, and cauſing her to ſpend in following it aboue 60. pound for upſhot of all, exſpecting a full ſertificate to this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee to have her mony, and being before the Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee, the ſaid <hi>Andrews</hi> and one <hi>Lownes,</hi> both ſpeciall inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of <hi>Breretons, Bradſhaw</hi> helping at a dead lift, informe that my wife had ſpoken words againſt the Parliament, <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> makes uſe of this, and the words muſt be receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as new matter againſt her, they are asked if the words were that the Parliament were Traytors, they anſwer they were much to that purpoſe, the queſtion againe put with humming and hawing give the ſame anſwer, it is then put that poſitively upon their oathes did ſhee ſay the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament were Traitors, and did you here <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſpeake the words, they anſwered ſhee did, at which their villany and purjurie ſhee was more aſtoniſhed to haere, then troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led at all her loſſes, and this purjurie was by the wiſe Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giant <hi>Wild<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> adjudged good payment of her monies, but admitted the words true, I pray judge whether it is provid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or ment in the ordinance, to make a Womans tongue under ſo heavie loſſes a Delinquent.</p>
            <p>To enlarge my ſelfe farther of all my ſufferings upon this falſe foundation, and the villains both countenanced and act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon me and my famelie theſe 4 yeares 8 monthes, and to tell you that <hi>Andrews</hi> in his mallice, and by his firme ſupporters by advantage of theſe times, when <hi>Bradſhaw</hi> and <hi>Steele</hi> have laid a ſide their old law books, how they have laid at my ſon to ruin him, and the proceeding therein would preſent to an undeſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing man that had for 7. yeare beene abſent in farre parts, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:160485:9"/>heard what and how the affaires of this Kingdome have beene carried, and to heare but as to my particulars, ſuch a loſſe of the good old lawes in force, at the time he left us a happie Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wonder and hardly be brought to beleeve ſuch things could be done, a Parliament ſitting in England,</p>
            <p>To make an end you have my impriſonment for cauſe and time, the Committee proceeding, and by that my unrecoverable ruine of me and my familie, my endeavours uſed by appeale to the houſe of Commons obſtructed, I ſhall tell you but one mote, and that is when lawes are of no uſe to protect honeſt men, the commons truſtes not to be protective to their truſters, the mixt Committee of Lords and Commons as to my caſe, and as you have heard ſo quick in Iudgement, but ſlo to come to it, that exſpences and attendance will ſoone undoe a better man then they have left me, to bring a good cauſe to a hearing, after all and for the ſpace of a yeare and two months paſt ſince, I did periti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the houſe of Lords, and appealed with deſire to be heard, but no anſwer for that yeare, 2. months ſince renned my petition<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> had for anſwer of one particular Lord they were tied up tanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to doe no man right or juſtice, if the complaint concerned the houſe of Commons, ſo no juſtice to be had in houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, againſt a vote of a Committee, no lawes to protect, no Lords to relieve, and opreſſions thus continuing on me, I have made recoverede to the lawes taken poſſeſſion of my own, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed of the lawes protection, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e I finde an Army which banne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> againſt me, and Club <hi>Law</hi> Captaine Clowne and his trained ſoldiers full charged againſt me, a Committes that beleeves all honeſty and lawes are to be cleane forgotten, and that to perpetuate their lawleſſe, cheating and villanies, have by the power and the Trained bands, impriſoned 9 poore labouring men for working in my worke, and in my own ground, and for no other cauſe, broken open my barne, and continuing Captaine <hi>Clowne</hi> &amp; his lawleſſe, violence and riot all day, carried away all the corne by night. What can be ſand when a ſort of men degenerate in to brute beaſts are countenanced in theſe lawleſſe, villanes, I may ſay they are more wolves and beares then thoſe brute beaſts themſelves, for they in their kinde are peaceable among themſelves, and bite not one another, whereas con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary the mallice of theſe men give them no content, but in tearing and ſpoyling of others, Now heare O Heavens and conſider O earth, if the like oppreſſions were ever heard of in our fore Fathers times, as I have here truly ſtated, and all honeſt men will have a ſence and feeling of my condition, I may juſtly ſay a fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low feeling with me, nor to a few &amp; the good God of Heaven, earth &amp; all honeſt men look on our miſeries and in thy good tune ſend us deliverance, ever are the prayers and the ſteadfaſt aſſureance of <hi>Thomas Connigs by.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
